我这里有一个规则的点网格。我们将看看这些点是如何移动的
What I have here is a regular grid of dots. We are going to look at how those dots move
在相机移动时在相机的图像平面中。
in the image plane of a camera as the camera moves.
在这里，我们让相机看着那个网格点;我要移动相机
Here we have the camera looking at that grid of dots; and I am going to move the camera
向左-这是负X方向-我们可以说是点
towards the left — that's the negative X direction — and we can say that the dots
所有这些都在图像平面中沿正X方向移动。回到中间
all appear to move in the positive X direction in the image plane. Come back to the middle
现在我沿着正Y方向移动相机。我们看到所有的点都出现了
and now I move the camera in the positive Y direction. We see the dots all appear to
在框架中向上移动;这是在负Y方向。如果我向下移动相机
move upward in the frame; that's in the negative Y direction. If I move the camera downwards
朝着点的平面，我们看到它们都倾向于向外扩展
towards the plane of the dots, we see that they all tend to be expanding outwards from
图像平面的中心。最后，如果我绕Z轴旋转相机-那是什么
the centre of the image plane. And finally, if I rotate the camera around its Z axis — what's
称为光轴-我们看到所有点都围绕中心旋转
called the optic axis — we see that the dots all appear to rotate around the centre
图像平面。
of the image plane.
考虑一下我们有一个相机看着一个物体，在这种情况下是一个球。
Consider that we have a camera looking at an object, in this case a ball.
我们以一种我们应该非常熟悉的方式将坐标框架附加到相机上
We attach a coordinate frame to the camera in a way that we should be quite familiar
与现在。我们称之为坐标系C.现在我们可以定义球的位置
with now. We call that coordinate frame C. Now we can define the position of the ball
关于坐标框架C.现在我们可以认为相机是可以的
with respect to coordinate frame C. Now we can consider that the camera is able
移动，它在三维空间中移动，所以我们可能有一个速度
to move, and it's moving in three-dimensional space so we can have potentially a velocity
在X，Y和Z方向上，它可以绕X，Y和Z轴旋转。
in the X, Y and Z directions, and it can rotate about the X, Y and Z axis.
我们可以将球的三维位置投影到图像平面中并获得
We can project the three dimensional position of the ball into the image plane and we obtain
坐标u，v。
the coordinate u,v.
让我们在MATLAB中演示一些这些想法。
Let's demonstrate some of these ideas in MATLAB.
我们要创建一个相机对象，我们之前遇到过这个。这是针孔
We are going to create a camera object, and we've encountered this before. It's a pinhole
具有默认参数的摄像机，这些显示在此处。我要创造一个观点
camera with default parameters, and these are shown here. I am going to create a point
在世界上，它将是一米的X坐标，一米的Y坐标，Z坐标
in the world and it's going to be X coordinate of a metre, Y coordinate of a metre, Z coordinate
五米转置，使其成为列向量。现在我可以预测
of five metres. Transpose that so that it is a column vector. Now I can project that
三维世界指向我相机的图像平面，它就在这个坐标上
three-dimensional world point onto the image plane of my camera, and it is at this coordinate
-672foru，672forv。现在我要重新指出这一点，
- 672 for u, 672 for v. Now I am going to project the point again,
但是这次我要换相机。我可以用'tcam'选项做到这一点-
but this time I am going to shift the camera. I can do that with the ‘tcam’ option — the
摄像机的变换-我将在X方向上移动相机0.1米。
transform of the camera — and I am going to move the camera 0.1 metres in the X direction.
所以我们之前遇到的'transl'函数创建了一个齐次变换
So the ‘transl’ function we've encountered before creates a homogeneous transformation
代表翻译。此平移中没有旋转：X方向为0.1，
that represents a translation. There's no rotation in this translation: 0.1 in X direction,
Y方向0米，Z方向0米。
0 metres in the Y direction, 0 metres in the Z direction.
关闭最后一个括号，这就是重点。
Close that last bracket off, and here is the point.
我在正X方向上移动了一小部分相机，我们可以看到
I've moved the camera a small amount in the positive X direction, and we can see that
你的坐标减少了。该点已在图像中向左移动。
the u coordinate has reduced. The point has moved toward the left in the image.
我可以通过获取移位之间的差异来计算此运动的灵敏度
I can compute the sensitivity of this motion by taking the difference between the shifted
点，及其原始位置，除以我移动相机的数量。这个
point, and its original position, and dividing by the amount that I moved the camera. This
灵敏度表示对于每个仪表我在正X方向上移动相机，
sensitivity indicates that for every metre that I move the camera in the positive X direction,
投影将在图像平面上移动-160像素。
the projection will move -160 pixels on the image plane.
我们可以为其他类型的相机运动重复此过程。
We can repeat this process for other kinds of camera motion.
这是我们对世界点的投射函数，我现在要翻译它
Here is our projection function of the world point, and I am going to now translate the
相机在Z方向。减去原始位置除以0.1，我们在这里看到
camera in the Z direction. Subtract the original position and divide by 0.1, and here we see
如果我沿Z方向移动相机1米，这个特定的点会移动
that if I move the camera 1 metre in the Z direction, this particular point will move
u方向为32像素，v方向为32像素。我可以替换那个翻译
32 pixels in the u direction, 32 pixels in the v direction. I can replace that translation
旋转。让我们旋转相机，比如围绕X轴的0.1弧度，然后重复，
with a rotation. Let's rotate the camera, say 0.1 radians around the X axis and repeat,
在这种特殊情况下，点的投影将移动40像素
and in this particular case the projection of the point will move by 40 something pixels
在u方向和850像素-在v方向上的大量运动。
in the u direction and 850 pixels — a significant amount of motion in the v direction.
我们看到的是我如何移动相机和投影方式之间的关系
What we've seen is the relationship between how I move the camera and how the projection
在图像平面上有所不同。
varies on the image plane.
可视化这里发生的事情的更直观的方法是显示流场，和
A more intuitive way to visualise what's going on here is to display the flow field, and
为这个特定的摄像机定义了流场，我传递了速度
the flow field is defined for this particular camera and I pass in the velocity of the
相机。所以在这种情况下，我将传递相机的空间速度，所以
camera. So in this case I am going to pass in the spatial velocity of the camera, so
这是一个六向量，它在X方向上有单位速度。流场看起来像
that's a six vector and it has got unit velocity in the X direction. The flow field looks like
这个。它说如果摄像机正向X方向移动，那么每个点都是如此
this. It's saying that if the camera is moving in the positive X direction, then every point
在图像中将向左移动。如果我将相机速度更改为单位
in the image will be shifted towards the left. If I change the camera velocity to be unit
在Y方向上的速度，然后流场看起来像这样。如果我的相机在移动
velocity in the Y direction, then the flow field looks like this. If my camera is moving
在正Y方向，这是我定义我的相机坐标框架的方式-
in the positive Y direction, which is the way I defined my camera coordinate frame — the
相机在世界上向下移动-然后图像中的每个点都向上移动。
camera is moving downwards in the world — then every point in the image appears to move upwards.
现在让我们将速度改为Z方向的单位速度。想象一下相机
Now let's change the velocity to being unit velocity in the Z direction. Imagine the camera
正在走向现场。现在，流场看起来像这样。我们有这个非常独特的
is moving towards the scene. Now the flow field looks like this. We have this very distinctive
来自图像平面中心的辐射图案。
radiating pattern coming from the centre of the image plane.
我要向你展示的最后一个例子是零平移运动而且它有
The final example that I want to show you has got zero translational motion and it has
获得围绕Z轴的单位旋转运动。我正在旋转相机，在这种情况下，
got unit rotational motion around the Z axis. I'm rotating the camera and in this case,
场景中的每个点似乎都围绕图像平面的中心旋转。
every point in the scene appears to rotate around the centre of the image plane.
让我们考虑一下我们有一个常规的点阵列，而摄像机正在移动
Let's consider that we have a regular array of points and the camera is moving in the
正X方向。它有一个正X速度分量。我们观察到的是
positive X direction. It's got a positive X velocity component. What we observe is that
图像中的所有点均匀向左移动。现在让我们考虑更多
all the points in the image move uniformly toward the left. Now let's consider a more
有趣的例子，相机向前移动。现在我们看到的是这个有趣的
interesting example where the camera is moving forward. And now what we see is this interesting
辐射效果，有点像星际迷航的翘曲速度效果。我们看到了这一点
radiating effect, a bit like the Star Trek warp speed effect. We see that points towards
图像的边缘比图像中间的点移动得更快。中心
the edge of the image are moving faster than points in the middle of the image. The centre
我们称之为扩张的焦点。这是所有像素的点
of the image we call the focus of expansion. It's the point from which all of the pixels
似乎是放射出来的。现在考虑我们将相机向正方向旋转
appear to be radiating from. Consider now that we rotate the camera in a positive direction
围绕Z轴。如果我拿着相机，这将对应我旋转相机
around the Z axis. If I’m holding the camera, that will correspond to me rotating the camera
顺时针方向。像素速度的模式现在非常不同。我们看
in a clockwise direction. The pattern of pixel velocities is now quite different. We see
每个像素的速度与以图像中间为中心的圆相切。
that each pixel's velocity is tangential to a circle centred on the middle of the image.
到目前为止，我们已经考虑过一个相当人为的例子。我们想象这台相机正在移动
So far, we've considered a fairly contrived example. We've imagined this camera moving
朝着一个统一的点阵。现实世界不是那样，但我们可以计算
towards a uniform array of dots. The real world is not like that, but we can compute
这种光流现象用于真实图像序列。在这里，我们看到一些图像
this optical flow phenomena for real image sequences. Here we see some imagery which
从无人驾驶飞行器捕获，如果你愿意，可以使用飞行机器人。机器人在飞
is captured from an unmanned aerial vehicle, a flying robot if you like. The robot is flying
在非常恒定的高度，并在非常直线上移动。每一个
at pretty much constant altitude, and moving in very much a straight line. Each of these
绿色箭头表示图像中的一个点从一帧移动的方向
green arrows indicates the direction that a point in the image is moving from one frame
到下一个。这种像素运动在帧与帧之间被夸大了。一点是
to the next. This pixel motion has been greatly exaggerated from frame to frame. A point is
只会移动几个像素。虽然平均像素速度在内部向下
only going to move a few pixels. Although the average pixel velocity is downwards within
在图像中，我们还可以看到有一些左右运动，这表明
the image, we can also see that there is some side to side motion, and this would indicate
然后，机器人并没有完全沿着直线路径飞行-也许正在受到冲击
then that the robot is not exactly flying a straight-line path - perhaps is being buffeted
通过阵风导致其航向角稍微改变。
by wind gusts which is causing its heading angle to change a little bit.
另一个例子是这个更具三维性的例子，是从一辆汽车上的摄像头拍摄的
Another example, this one which is more three-dimensional, is taken from a camera on a car moving along
一条路，旁边有很多停放的汽车，有很多树木。
a road, and there are a lot of parked cars at the side and there are a lot of trees.
在这种特殊情况下你会注意到的是远处的物体相对而言
What you'll notice in this particular case is that objects that are far away cause relatively
光流很小，靠近的物体会产生大量的光流，
little optical flow, where objects that are close by cause a large amount of optical flow,
而靠近的物体会产生大量的光流。我们可以看到这一点
whereas objects that are close by cause a large amount of optical flow. We can see this
再次辐射光流模式。我们可以看到向量都显示出辐射
radiating optical flow pattern again. We can see that the vectors all appear to radiate
从汽车前面的一点，我们称之为扩张的焦点。这才是重点
from a point in front of the car, which we call the focus of expansion. That's the point
在汽车正朝着这个世界的方向发展。我们偶尔会注意到的另一件事
in the world that the car is heading towards. Another thing we will notice occasionally
是光流向量疯狂地上下跳动，这是因为汽车
is that the optical flow vectors bounce up and down crazily, and that's because the car
正在开车超速。所以汽车正在向上倾斜，然后向下倾斜。那
was driving over a speed bump. So the car is pitching up and then pitching down. That
引起附加的运动分量，其叠加在光流的顶部
causes an additional motion component, which is superimposed on top of the optical flow
由于纯粹的前进动作。
due to just pure forward motion.
这是一种非常强大的错觉。我在旋转的鼓内，我的眼睛可以检测到
This is a very very powerful illusion. I am inside a rotating drum and my eye can detect
鼓的动作。我的眼睛和大脑正在计算我们所谓的光流，并且
the motion of this drum. My eye and my brain are computing what we call optical flow, and
由旋转鼓引起的这种光流是与那种光流相同的
this optical flow that's caused by that rotating drum, is the same sort of optical flow that
如果我以这种方式转动头部，或者我以这种方式旋转头部，我就会得到。而这种特殊的错觉
I get if I rotate my head this way, or I rotate my head that way. And this particular illusion
让我觉得有点不安，因为我用眼睛得到的信息-
causes me to feel a little bit uneasy because the information that I get with my eyes — the
光流-告诉我，我的头部正在从一侧移动到另一侧但是陀螺仪
optical flow — tells me that my head is moving from side to side but the gyroscopic
在我耳边的传感器告诉我，那不会发生。所以两者之间存在脱节
sensors in my ears tell me that that's not happening. So there is a disconnect between
我的耳朵告诉我我的态度，以及我的眼睛讲述我的动作，
what my ears are telling me about my attitude, and what my eyes are telling about my motion,
这导致了晕船或轻微恶心的感觉，这就是我挂的原因
and that leads to the sensation of sea sickness or slight nausea, which is why I am hanging
紧紧地对着这些铁轨。
on very tightly to these rails.